$("document").ready(function () {
    var gameQuestions = [{
        question: 'How many licks to a center of a tootsie pop?',
        choices: ['1', '100', '400', '364'],
        correctAnswer: 3
    }, {
        question: 'What is the only mammal that can truly fly?',
        choices: ['Bat', 'Eagle', 'Wombat', 'Chicken'],
        correctAnswer: 0
    }, {
        question: 'Which continent is also a country?',
        choices: ['Australia', 'South America', 'Russia', 'United Kingdom'],
        correctAnswer: 0
    }, {
        question: 'The Bill of Rights contains how many of the first amendments to the United States Constitution?',
        choices: ['Five', 'Ten', 'Twenty-Seven', 'Nine'],
        correctAnswer: 1
    }, {
        question: 'Who was first to implement a assembly line for the mass production of cars?',
        choices: ['Ford', 'General Motors', 'Chevy', 'Dodge'],
        correctAnswer: 0
    }, {
        question: 'Which continent has the highest human population density?',
        choices: ['Europe', 'Asia', 'South America', 'North America'],
        correctAnswer: 1

    }, {
        question: '1993 theme park from cloned dinosaurs?',
        choices: ['Jurassic World', 'Jurassic Parks', 'Jurassic Parc', 'Jurassic Park'],
        correctAnswer: 3
    }, {
        question: 'In what ocean did the Titanic sink?',
        choices: ['South Pacific Ocean', 'North Pacific Ocean', 'South Atlantic Ocean', 'North Atlantic Ocean'],
        correctAnswer: 3
    }, {
        question: 'What was the first console game that allowed the game to be saved?',
        choices: ['Zelda', 'Legend of Zelda', 'Ocarina of Time', 'Twilight Princess'],
        correctAnswer: 1
    }, {
        question: 'What is the heaviest naturally occurring element found on Earth?',
        choices: ['Diamonds', 'Steel', 'Uranium', 'Granite'],
        correctAnswer: 2
    }, {
        question: 'What is the most abundant element in the earthâ€™s atmosphere?',
        choices: ['Nitrogen', 'Oxygen', 'Argon', 'Hydrogen'],
        correctAnswer: 0
    }];



    // timer for the question form when user clicks the start button
    $("#start").on("click", function () {
        var number = 121;
        var intervalId;
        var correct = 0;
        var wrong = 0;

        function questionCounter (){
            correctAnswer();
            wrongAnswer();
        }
        questionCounter();
        function correctAnswer () {
        $("#correct").html(0);
    }
        function wrongAnswer () {
        $("#wrong").html(0);
    }
        function setCountDown() {
            clearInterval(intervalId);
            intervalId = setInterval(countdown, 1000);
        }

        function countdown() {
            number--;
            $("#time").html("<h2>" + "Time Left:" + number + "</h2>");
            if (number === 0) {
                location.reload();
                alert("Time Up! You lose!");
            }
        }
        setCountDown();


        $("#start").hide();

        var html = createUlHtml(gameQuestions);
        $("#quizarea").append(html);
        $("#correct").show();
        $("#wrong").show();
        $("p").show();



        // gives unique ID's to the span and list items
        $("span").on("click", function () {
            var liIndex = (parseInt(this.parentElement.id) / 10) - 1;

            var liid = parseInt(this.parentElement.id);
            var spanIndex = parseInt(this.id) - liid - 1;

            //   console.log("liIndex = " + liIndex);
            //   console.log("spanIndex " + spanIndex);
            //   console.log("gameQuestions = " + gameQuestions[liIndex]);
            //   console.log("choices = " + gameQuestions[liIndex].choices[spanIndex]);

            if (spanIndex === gameQuestions[liIndex].correctAnswer) {
                alert("correct answer " + gameQuestions[liIndex].choices[spanIndex]);
               gameQuestions.choices.hide();

            } else {
                alert("wrong, correct answer is " + gameQuestions[liIndex].choices[gameQuestions[liIndex].correctAnswer]);

            }

        });
    });
});

function createUlHtml(gameQuestions) {
    var liid = 0;
    var spanid = liid;
    var html = "";
    //for loop that adds the questions to the page 
    for (i = 0; i < gameQuestions.length; i++) {
        liid = liid + 10;
        spanid = liid + 1;
        html = html + "<li id=" + liid + ">" + gameQuestions[i].question +
            "<span id=" + spanid++ + ">" + gameQuestions[i].choices[0] + "</span>,  " +
            "<span id=" + spanid++ + ">" + gameQuestions[i].choices[1] + "</span>,  " +
            "<span id=" + spanid++ + ">" + gameQuestions[i].choices[2] + "</span>, " +
            "<span id=" + spanid + ">" + gameQuestions[i].choices[3] + "</span></li> ";
    }
    return html;

}